+49 163 9078036 Karlsruhe | Vienna roshanprizak@gmail.com roshanprizak.com

ROSHAN PRIZAK

DATA SCIENTIST

https://www.linkedin.com/in/roshan-prizak-05a185254/

About me

Skilled data scientist with 9+ years experience in data analysis, statistical analysis, data modelling, data visualisation, research paper writing and collaborative research projects. Strong quantitative background in pure and applied mathematics, statistics, data analysis, and computer science. Driven to learn new tools and concepts, actively building an independent data science portfolio on real-world problems.

General Skills

Data scraping

Data cleaning

Data mining

Data modeling

Data visualization

Hypothesis testing

Statistical analysis

(Regression analysis

Markov Chain Monte Carlo

Deep learning

Machine learning

Technical Skills

Programming/libraries:

Python, R Programming, R Markdown, R Shiny, MATLAB, C++, Bash, SQL, D3.js, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Vue.js, Quasar, scikit-learn, Tensorflow, matplotlib, ggplot2, Plotly, Leaflet

Other software/tools:

Firebase, Node.js, AWS, Canva, GitHub, git, LaTeX, conda, Docker

Soft Skills

- Collaboration
- Communication
- Multi-tasking
- Leadership
- Decision-making
- Critical thinking
- · Quick learner
- · Out-of-box thinking

Data Science Projects

How accessible is Vienna's public transport? 🔗 📵





- Using GTFS feeds, database of addresses and a local Docker-based installation of openrouteservice, built a dataset of closest public transport
- Visualized results in a R Shiny interactive app, and deployed it on AWS.
- Next, using routing and real-time info, quantify first-mile and last-mile connectivity, robustness to cancellations, redundancy and other metrics

NLP analysis of the resolutions of the World Health Assembly 🔗 📵



- Using NLP techniques and network analysis, uncovered topics and patterns behind the resolutions adopted by the sessions of the WHA
- Created a clean dataset of WHA resolutions from all WHA sessions by obtaining PDFs, converting to text using PyPDF2 and cleaning it

Age gaps between lead male & female actors in Indian cinema 🤌



- Extracted and clean data from Wikipedia and other public sources
- Visualized the age gaps using matplotlib

Looking at cricket through numbers 🔗



- Extract ball-by-ball details batter, bowler, fielding, events, commentary from ESPNCricinfo, ICC and other sources and prepare a clean dataset
- Translate qualitative questions about player strategies, performances, umpire biases, team predictions etc. into quantitative insights

Positions

Karlsruhe Institute of Technology

Postdoctoral scientist



Mar 2019 - Present

Key responsibilities:

- Image and data analysis of complex microscopy datasets
- Bioinformatics analysis of large-scale genomic data
- Physical modeling and polymer simulations of chromatin, followed by data analysis of simulation output data in Python
- Worked as part of multiple research teams, contributed to various projects and co-wrote published research papers
- Supervised students, taught R and Python to Master and students



Austria Model World Health Organization

Vice-President

Aug 2022 - Present

Key responsibilities:

- Co-organised simulations of the World Health Assembly
- Designed and deployed website at austriamodelwho.org
- Co-wrote theme guides for Austria Model WHO simulations
 - Energy Security and Health (October 2022)
 - Climate Change and Health (April 2023)
- Admin roles delegate training during simulations, dissemination material design

+49 163 9078036 Karlsruhe | Vienna roshanprizak@gmail.com roshanprizak.com

ROSHAN PRIZAK

DATA SCIENTIST



https://www.linkedin.com/in/roshan-prizak-05a185254/

Teaching

Data Analysis, Statistics and R

as part of Chemomics and Phenomics Instructor (MFOR-3209, KIT, 2022) Instructor (MFOR-3209, KIT, 2021)

Making graphs with Python

as part of Python Applications Instructor (BIF-IGS course, KIT, 2023) Instructor (BIF-IGS course, KIT, 2022)

Selected Topics in Biophysics

Teaching Assistant (IST Austria, 2014)

Network Theory (EE 224)

Teaching Assistant (IIT Bombay, 2012)

Courses

- Data analysis
- Statistical physics
- Statistics
- Biophysics
- Bioinformatics
- Core electrical engineering
- Pure and applied math (number theory, real and complex analysis, linear algebra, DDEs, PDEs, probability theory, optimization, Markov processes, Markov chains)
- Machine learning and Al
- Systems and networks

Languages

Fluent/native

English Telugu Hindi A2+ **A1+**

German Spanish Tamil Kannada

Malayalam

Education Background



Institute of Science and Technology Austria

PhD student

Sept 2013 - Dec 2018

Bioinformatics, biophysics, evolutionary theory





Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (GPA 8.63/10)

Master of Technology Bachelor of Technology July 2008 - Aug 2013

Electrical Engineering (Communication & Signal Processing)



Internships

Institute of Science and Technology Austria

May 2012 - July 2012

University of Surrey, UK

May 2011 - July 2011

Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, India May 2010 - July 2010

Awards and honours

Heinz Scholarship for graduate education (IST Austria, 2013 - 2016)

Rajiv Gandhi Science Talent Research Fellow (Bangalore, 2010 - 2011)

CBSE Merit Scholarship for undergraduate education (India, 2008 - 2010)

Ranked 125 out of 300,000 applicants in IIT-JEE (India, 2008)

Gold Medal, top 25 at camp for International Chemistry Olympiad (India, 2008)

Among top 42 in the Indian National Chemistry Olympiad (India, 2008)

Top 1% in the National Science Examination in Physics (India, 2008)